The milk commercials never mention
calcium in my arteries, only in my
bones. Odd. Well, that's because clean
arteries, those dynamic pipes delivering
blood full of nutrients, oxygen, and
more, are supposed to be calcium free in
an ideal scenario. If you've uh ever
heard of the CAC score, the coronary
artery calcium score, which measures the
amount of can you guess it? Correct.
Cheese. no calcium found in your
arteries. The higher your CAC score, the
worse your risk of a major
cardiovascular event, which is a fancy
way of saying that your ticker is going
to stop you from continuing your current
existence. So, it makes sense to want to
make sure that one's calcium score is on
the lower end. I need to stress this
upfront. There's a huge
caveat to that. I probably could have
continued that. that we'll get into
later. But overall, yes, greater calcium
levels in the arteries is linked to
greater heart disease. Well, it turns
out that a particular extremely
important mineral plays a role in if you
develop calcium in your arteries or not.
Or at least that's what this study has
to say and is going to try to show. And
if you're literate, you know that that
mineral is potassium. So, what happens
when we're potassium deficient? And does
it actually matter in the broader
context of cardiovascular health? Here
the researchers fed mice that were
especially prone to developing
cardiovascular disease through plaque
buildup in the arteries of one of three
diets. A low potassium diet, a moderate
potassium diet, which is our control
condition, or
a high potassium diet. What we're
looking at here is an H& stain and an
alazarin stain. Both of which are ways
to detect calcium in the artery. The
most prominent is the alzarin red stain
which stains calcium deposits in red.
And as you can clearly see that in the
low potassium group, there's these big
deposits of calcium. In fact, we even
see it a bit in the control condition,
but we don't seem to see it in the high
potassium group. But these are
representative images. So if we look at
the averages, we can see a step-wise
reduction in arterial calcification
right here. In fact, this is further
corroborated when looking at overall
arterial, in this case the aorta, a
massive artery stiffness. This
particular measure takes into
consideration more than calcification,
but it echoes a similar trends measured
by pulse wave velocity. I think these
images are especially striking because
this is a slice of the aorta. So the
white section is where the blood would
flow and the dark red is the
calcification stain. Again, in a
step-wise fashion, we can see lower
potassium levels indicating massively
more calcification. Yet higher potassium
has none. Okay, we get the picture.
Potassium good, no potassium bad. The
next question is why is this happening?
Because we know that potassium is
critical for maintaining our brain
function and heart rhythm as it's
instrumentally kept inside of our cells
in an inactive state but is exchanged
during activated states. But what's
happening in the artery cells? By artery
cells I mean smooth muscle cells which
are the cells that directly control the
contraction and relaxation of your blood
vessels itself. These uh muscle cells
found in the deeper sections of the
arterial wall play a critical role in
maintaining blood pressure by opening
the blood vessel to drop blood pressure
and constricting the blood vessel to
increase blood pressure. However, in
advancing stages of cardiovascular
disease, these smooth muscle cells will
do a few things that are important
aspects of advanced atherosclerosis or
plaque growth. One, they'll
means that they act less like muscle
cells and begin acting more like another
type of cell. Second, they migrate,
meaning that they move from the deeper
regions of the blood vessel wall to the
surface. But our focus is on the first
change, the differentiation. Check this
out. I find this fascinating and it
gives us a crazy cool clue. Here we're
measuring the calcium content inside
these smooth muscle cells at varying
levels of potassium exposure. At low
potassium exposure, the cells suck up
calcium like a vacuum cleaner. And it
isn't until greater concentrations that
calcium gets slashed. This gives us a
clue because it might mean that the
cells are suddenly acting less like
smooth muscle cells and more like well
if we go back to my very first comment
the milk commercials never mention
calcium in my arteries only in my bones.
Odd. What cells are in your bones? Bone
cells. Correctto or more technically
osteoccytes. So, are these still
vascular smooth muscle cells or are they
turned like zombies? Well, let's test
it. There's these three molecules that
are being measured here. Runx 2, OC, and
ALP. RNX 2 here is an osteoblast
differentiation factor, meaning it's
heavily involved in convincing stem
cells without an identity to turn into
bone cells called osteoblasts. OC or
osteocalin there is a protein that binds
calcium and is secreted by mature
osteoblasts.
Those are the same bone cells. Uh-oh. I
think uh our smooth muscle may not be a
smooth muscle cell anymore. The reason I
say that is because the gene expression
of these bone cell factors are increased
only in the low potassium conditions.
But to confirm we can look at the
opposite that happens to be the muscle
centric genes. Here we're looking at two
muscle genes like alpha smooth muscle
actin which is a protein involved in the
contraction of muscle cell. It's moving
in the opposite direction. So reduced
potassium exposure indicates reduced
expression of these genes. So in
summary, more bone genes, fewer muscle
genes. So yeah, our artery cells become
more like bone cells, even if we'd
likely need more evidence to say that
they're fully converted. The point
being, they're giving off cell
signatures that indicate these cells are
more prone to releasing calcium for
deposition. What a remarkable discovery.
Now, there's more important context that
would be applied here, and how do we
actually use this information? We'll get
into that shortly. But there's also some
autophagy, some cell self-cleaning
aspects to this, as well as some
fascinating mechanisms that change
inside of our cells that if you're
interested, I'm covering in the full
analysis, the extended version of this
video found within the depths of the
physionic insiders, my premium research
platform. And if you even want to nerd
out in live sessions where we discuss
this kind of stuff together, consider
joining the insiders. The link is in the
description. Oh, there's uh plenty of
other benefits of being a member, too,
but uh I've covered them at nauseium, so
I'll leave it for the curious minds to
discover. Link is in the description.
Okay, context. I don't know about you,
but I've never been accused of being a
mouse. I mean, a dashingly good-looking
dude. Sure. Thank you. Thank you. Oh,
stop at you. I'm blushing.
There's really no need What's that?
Oh, you you weren't talking to me.
Let's uh let's move on. Uh the point
being this is a mouse study and they're
incredibly informative for mechanistic
research, but we need to make sure that
they're applicable parallels in human
research. The researchers do mention
there are correlations between low
potassium and increased cardiovascular
disease. In fact, we've covered these
studies before. Still, that's a general
relationship and it doesn't actually
speak to the actual calcification
itself. They do mention there are some
studies in humans where affecting some
of the mechanisms by which potassium
works is directly related to reduced
calcification in our arteries. Okay, not
bad, but still not foolproof evidence. I
also ran across this small associative
study that did find that higher
potassium levels correlated with less
severe artery calcium. And again, this
is far from conclusive data. Overall, I
don't think it's far-fetched to say that
potassium may help reduce the
calcification of our arteries, but
there's definitely need for more studies
to implicate it directly in humans. What
we do know is that potassium helps in
other cardiovascular centric ways. So,
it's not exactly a gamble to increase
one's potassium intake if it's uh low.
But, there's an additional consideration
here that I should mention. I hinted at
it earlier. The thing is, we demonize
calcification in our arteries as a
necessarily terrible thing, but there
are contexts where calcification is
probably a positive thing if all else is
held equal. And that's key. For example,
we know soft plaque, the non-calcified
plaque in our in atherosclerosis driven
cardiovascular disease is more dangerous
than calcified plaque. So if we have
equal amounts of plaque, the more
calcified a plaque is, the more stable
it is. On the other hand, between having
no plaque versus calcified plaque, no
plaque is without a doubt better.
There's more to say on that topic, but
the sole focus on calcification as a
risk indicator is likely incomplete,
even if we've uh been focus focusing on
it right here. So where does that leave
us then? Well, it still leaves us with
the overall literature indicating
potassium should be consumed within
reason. Overdoing it has its own
problems as it helps us combat
cardiovascular disease, possibly partly
through the calcification of the
arterial wall. Some excellent sources of
potassium in a non-exhaustive list are
apricots, uh, white beans, lima beans,
salmon, tuna, some yogurts, prunes, and
there's plenty of other sources. But
there's so much more potassium does to
protect our body. Check out this video
for that. Otherwise, if you want to
supplement with it, there's more info on
supplementation right here.